<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Life on rheneross</title><link>https://blog.thibaud.io/tags/life/</link><description>Recent content in Life on rheneross</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.thibaud.io/tags/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>When life gives you lemons</title><link>https://blog.thibaud.io/posts/2024_12_13/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.thibaud.io/posts/2024_12_13/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CM-CIvMEqUs">Don&amp;rsquo;t make lemonade&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m scared.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m an independent developer in the video game industry, and my current project is slowly wrapping up. I have enough savings to cover about 10 months of expenses, which might sound like a lot to some.
But this looming uncertainty — distant as it may be — keeps me up at night. I am deeply worried about not being able to provide for my family, so I&amp;rsquo;ve sent out resume everywhere&amp;hellip; and I got a job offer.&lt;br>
After hundreds of applications, tens of interviews, I got a job offer.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CM-CIvMEqUs">Don&rsquo;t make lemonade</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m scared.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m an independent developer in the video game industry, and my current project is slowly wrapping up. I have enough savings to cover about 10 months of expenses, which might sound like a lot to some.
But this looming uncertainty — distant as it may be — keeps me up at night. I am deeply worried about not being able to provide for my family, so I&rsquo;ve sent out resume everywhere&hellip; and I got a job offer.<br>
After hundreds of applications, tens of interviews, I got a job offer.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s an interesting technical subject, even if it&rsquo;s not in the game industry. It&rsquo;s a 15 minute ride from where I live, the culture seems really chill&hellip; but there&rsquo;s a catch:</p>
<p><strong>no remote work</strong>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been fully remote since 2018, and it allowed me to spend more time with my daughters, work on side projects, and even have the space to feel not-so-great from time to time.
I&rsquo;m not sure if I can handle a fully in-office job anymore.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s do a pros/cons list!</p>
<p>Pros:</p>
<ul>
<li>A stable job - Less money anxiety for me and my family</li>
<li>Working in one of the most advanced field in computer science</li>
<li>Literally 15 minutes away from my home</li>
<li>Flexible working hours</li>
</ul>
<p>Cons:</p>
<ul>
<li>A stable job - I really like the <em>free</em> part of freelancer</li>
<li>Not in the game industry</li>
<li>No remote work</li>
<li>No remote work — not even a little</li>
<li>No remote work — not at all</li>
<li>No remote work — <strong>NONE</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>WELL, looks like there&rsquo;s more cons 🙂</p>
<p>The thing is, I would love to have a bit of a break, to get time to work on my game engine and release some games made with it, maybe stream the process a bit?
I&rsquo;ll need to summon the courage to stay unemployed though.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s it, I&rsquo;m not caving, I&rsquo;m not taking the job.</p>
<p>I am not scared anymore.<br>
I will stay free, for now.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Here we go again</title><link>https://blog.thibaud.io/posts/2024_12_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 10:08:58 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.thibaud.io/posts/2024_12_2/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been journaling daily for about 10 years and, even in the privacy of my notebook, it&amp;rsquo;s been incredibly effective at taming the beast inside my head. Sometimes, though, I feel the urge to write something public and share it with the void.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, the urge returned: I&amp;rsquo;ve been fixating on ways to cooperate differently, especially in the game industry, and I had to get it out of my system. My previous attempt at a blog was retired at the time, so I went for the fastest way to publish anything: a newsletter platform. I wrote two articles, and then the emails flooded in. &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Grow your audience fast with fastaudiencegrowth&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em>, &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Subscribe to our premium platform and win your subscribers&amp;rsquo; weight in gold.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been journaling daily for about 10 years and, even in the privacy of my notebook, it&rsquo;s been incredibly effective at taming the beast inside my head. Sometimes, though, I feel the urge to write something public and share it with the void.</p>
<p>Recently, the urge returned: I&rsquo;ve been fixating on ways to cooperate differently, especially in the game industry, and I had to get it out of my system. My previous attempt at a blog was retired at the time, so I went for the fastest way to publish anything: a newsletter platform. I wrote two articles, and then the emails flooded in. <em>&ldquo;Grow your audience fast with fastaudiencegrowth&rdquo;</em>, <em>&ldquo;Subscribe to our premium platform and win your subscribers&rsquo; weight in gold.&rdquo;</em></p>
<p>Begone, devil! The void is my audience, and it shall not grow!</p>
<p>So, I dug back out my old blog, dusted it off, and published it again. I migrated the two articles and reclaimed my digital ownership! I even kept my old posts from 2022 — though I wouldn’t recommend diving too deep into them.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I was lucky to have my roots in websites because I always understood the value of building my own online spaces, and hosting everything that mattered to me on my own sites.<br>
— <!-- raw HTML omitted --><a href="https://www.nathalielawhead.com/candybox/positive-feedback-loops-the-power-of-choice-digital-independence-and-building-something-better-for-everyone">Nathalie Lawhead</a><!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have always value my digital independence, and I self-host a lot of services. I also believe that, as long as you control the source material, not everything needs to be <em>strictly</em> self-hosted. For example, this blog is a static site hosted on github pages and, even if github stop offering the service, I can move it somewhere else without loosing anything.</p>
<p>Aside from that, I&rsquo;ve been playing through my backlog a lot lately:</p>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve finished Portal Stories: Mel, a nice story for people wanting more Portal.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ve played a couple of chapters of Black Mesa, astonishing work!</li>
<li>I enjoyed Tinyfolks a lot. It&rsquo;s a tiny, more forgiving, Darkest Dungeon.</li>
<li>Clickholding: this one I can&rsquo;t say anything about, you&rsquo;d have to see it for yourself.</li>
<li>And lastly, I&rsquo;ve just started DREDGE, but I love it already :)</li>
</ul>
<p>Tinyfolks especially motivated me to start working on a tiny game - we&rsquo;ll see were it leads!</p>
<p>Until then, have a nice week and see you next time!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Rethinking collaboration models</title><link>https://blog.thibaud.io/posts/2024_10_17/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 11:15:14 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.thibaud.io/posts/2024_10_17/</guid><description>&lt;p>You know the feeling when you have a song stuck in your head? You have to sing it, you have to listen to it. Well, I tend to obsess like that about approximately everything. For example, I recently watched a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tsbCSkvHhMo">great video on quantum computing&lt;/a> and, even though I didn’t want to, I had to try and build a simulator. I would rather be making games, working on my actual job, or keeping a good sleep schedule; I just can’t help myself.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You know the feeling when you have a song stuck in your head? You have to sing it, you have to listen to it. Well, I tend to obsess like that about approximately everything. For example, I recently watched a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tsbCSkvHhMo">great video on quantum computing</a> and, even though I didn’t want to, I had to try and build a simulator. I would rather be making games, working on my actual job, or keeping a good sleep schedule; I just can’t help myself.</p>
<p>Over the years, journaling helped me a lot with over-obsessing, and I hope this newsletter will help me even more!</p>
<h2 id="weird-games">Weird Games</h2>
<p>This week I watched a great video on weird games (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=34NVLRHsxSU">part1</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oBrkdcVam4U">part2</a>). The video itself is in French, with some parts in English, but subtitles, written by the author, are available in both languages.</p>
<p>In the intro, someone says “I’m pessimistic about the industry, but optimistic about the medium” and this resonated quite a lot with me. I do believe we have to create new ways of financing video game production and new collaboration models, maybe taking inspiration from what communities are building in some &ldquo;third places&rdquo;.</p>
<h2 id="a-place-to-grow-food-and-be-creative">A place to grow food and be creative</h2>
<p>By third places, or “tiers lieu” in French, I mean <a href="https://www.equaltimes.org/the-revolution-of-the-third-place?lang=en&amp;utm_source=rheneross-newsletter.beehiiv.com&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=rethinking-collaboration-models">community spaces to work, share and collaborate</a>. In France, a lot of them are built around farming, co-working, creating art, or making objects. I would love to combine something like that with making games. A place where people can come, even stay multiple days, eat local food from the farm, and build games. The closest initiative I found, minus the farming, is in Sweden: <a href="https://www.spelkollektivet.com/">https://www.spelkollektivet.com/</a>.</p>
<p>Third places are also built to be more resilient: everyone can help everywhere and risks are split between each person in the collective and each activity. You can have farmers selling different kinds of vegetables, or game developers building different experiences, and everything evens out in the end.</p>
<p>And finally, as a lot of third places are open to the public, it’s a nice opportunity to teach game development or playtest games!</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! I hope you enjoyed 🙂<br>
Feel free to respond and tell me what you thought of this first issue!</p>
<p>Have a great week,<br>
Thibaud</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>